<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Darbadar</title>
    <description>Travel trails of two friends
</description>
    <link>http://darbadar.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://darbadar.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 30 Aug 2015 19:36:02 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 Aug 2015 19:36:02 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Rupin Pass Diaries - Day 1</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;Chaudhary, should we go to Himalayas once again?&quot;&gt;“Yaar Chaudhary, Himalayas chalein phir se?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;Which trek should we go on this time? I was thinking that we should do the Sikkim one...&quot;&gt;“Kaun se wale trek pe chalna hai? Main soch rahi thi wo Sikkim wala karein…”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I smiled. She had been making these plans for a long time, I could tell. After all, I had been too. 
And so, just like that, we sat, Harsha and I, making plans for our next trek in the Himalayas. A week later, we had an answer: Rupin pass, a high-altitude Himalayan trek that starts in Dhaula, Uttarakhand and ends in Sangla in Himachal Pradesh. Three weeks later, there was a change in plan. At least for one of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;America? That&#39;s so sudden! Why?&quot;&gt;“America? Achanak se! Kyun?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;Don&#39;t ask.&quot;&gt;“Pooch mat,”&lt;/em&gt; I sighed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So you aren’t coming? What the hell! How can you do this to me!” she overreacted as always.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;Don&#39;t know what she is high on all the time.&quot;&gt;“Pata nahi kya soong ke baithi rehti hai hamesha,”&lt;/em&gt; I muttered under my breath as she continued her rant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A month later, I was in Bellagio, Las Vegas, watching my mum try her luck at a slot machine when I received a call.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Hello Harsha,” I said distractedly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Hi! I called to tell you that I am leaving tomorrow.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Awesome!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am nervous…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of her sentence was drowned in a bout of frenzied celebration that my brother had just launched into. Mum had won a hundred dollars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Are you listening to me?” asked Harsha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yeah, yeah…don’t forget to write in your journal, I will read it once you are back, ok? Bye!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(A volley of curses followed, most inappropriate for a blog such as this.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day 1: Dhaula to Sewa&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the end of the trek today, I could feel all the extra cheese toppings on pizzas that I’ve been hogging for several weeks now, clogging my arteries. And this is just day one…at least I didn’t end up shooting vomit projectiles on the face of the mountains like I did the last time, on the first day of the KGL(Kashmir Great Lakes) trek.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sewa, our camp site, is like any other Garhwali village in Uttarakhand: all signs of modern life, including electricity, are missing. Not that I am complaining. It does get a little tiring keeping pace with life in the city. I love the simplicity of people and life here. They aren’t in a rush. They aren’t putting up a show. They live life as it is meant to be—simply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5741/20519090056_25313658e3_c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sewa&quot; data-caption=&quot;Idyllic, isn&#39;t it?&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The houses look like slightly larger versions of toys that children would play with. With their low roofs and small doors, and scattered as they are across lush green meadows, surrounded by coniferous trees, weighing down even the mighty mountains with the sheer strength of their numbers, one would expect Hobbits to step out of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5669/20357415080_e49edb6dd1_c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Houses of Sewa&quot; data-caption=&quot;Imagine waking up to that view every morning...&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I don’t think I would have been any more pleased to meet a Hobbit than I was to meet little Rohan and his grandfather Jaindra Singh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;Do you go to school?&quot;&gt;“Aap school jaate ho?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;Yes&quot;&gt;“Haan,”&lt;/em&gt; said Rohan, nodding vigorously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;Will you write your name here?&quot;&gt;“Aap apna naam likhoge yahan par?”&lt;/em&gt; I asked him, giving him my notebook and pen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;Yes&quot;&gt;“Haan,”&lt;/em&gt; he said and scribbled his name in my book in neat letters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;Oh nice! You write very well! Will you teach me how to write my name?&quot;&gt;“Arrey wah! Aap to bahut achcha likhte ho! Aap mujhe mera naam likhna sikhaoge?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;Yes&quot;&gt;“Haan,”&lt;/em&gt; he said his favourite four-letter word a third time, then went on to rechristen me as Harisha, and finally ran away abruptly, perhaps in anticipation of a full-blown, lethal round of elementary dictation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started scribbling in my notebook once more. After about five minutes, I was distracted by the sound of approaching footsteps. Maybe Rohan had changed his mind. I turned around. There he stood, sixty years older, the twinkle in those brown eyes still the same. I could swear it was Rohan. He was a spitting image of his grandfather Jaindra Singh, discounting the wrinkles of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;Where are you from?&quot;&gt;“Aap kahan se ho?”&lt;/em&gt; he asked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;From Pune, Maharashtra.&quot;&gt;“Pune, Maharastra se…”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;Where?&quot;&gt;“Kahan par?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;You must have heard of Mumbai...&quot;&gt;“Mumbai suna hoga apne…”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;Yes, absolutely. Where the movies are made!&quot;&gt;“Haan haan bilkul! Jahaan filme banti hain!”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter which part of India I travel to, however remote and oblivious to the rest of the country, if I’m ever struggling to find a common ground of discussion, talking about movies(/Mumbai, the place that churns them) always does the trick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t remember at which point the conversation steered from ‘Hum Aapke Hain Kaun’, a movie that he claimed to have watched over a dozen times, to his trips to Dehradun to sell apples from his orchard, but I was glad that it did, after all, nothing beats the charm of apple orchards, not even Madhuri Dixit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He talked about sending his children to school, about cold winters, and harsher than the cold winter summers in the mountains, about the symptoms of his existence, about everything that made his life everything that it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ease and generosity with which he let me take a peek into his life, astounded me. There he was, talking to me like we were long lost friends, seeking solace in the fact that his life, however mundane to him, was extraordinary to me, that his struggles made sense, even if just to a stranger he had barely known for a couple of minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is this candid attitude, fresh like the air and the water up here, that made me want to meet more people in Sewa. And I did. And they all treated me like I was family. And they all posed for me like ‘they do in the movies’. I have never seen happiness as I saw on their faces. While most of us spend our lives pursuing happiness, these people, somehow, seem to be born right into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5776/20357401110_3485c93a35_c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kid&quot; data-caption=&quot;When I shot him for the first time, he wasn&#39;t too happy with the results. He suggested &#39;I press the button better&#39; a second time. I think it worked.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5747/20358759799_2bfd2d0411_c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Other People&quot; data-caption=&quot;No fancy baby food. Or diapers. Still happy as a clam.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that I will fade in their minds faster than the seconds hand changes places on a clock, but the people of Sewa will forever hold a special place in my heart. Especially Rohan and his grandfather.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jaindra Singh was thrilled when I took his photograph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;I don&#39;t have a single photograph. I never needed one.&quot;&gt;“Humne aaj tak photo nahi khinchai apni. Zaroorat hi nahi padi…”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5783/20357445518_29b85fcd9b_c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jaindra Singhji&quot; data-caption=&quot;Doesn&#39;t he look like an overgrown child?&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I promised to send him a print of the photograph. I know for a fact that I will. Even though I know that it is highly unlikely that it will ever reach him, to this place lost in time, with no postal code…if it does, I hope that it finds a place in that hole in the wall of their house that they hold sacred, where Rohan’s books rest, and the spiders spin their webs next to the tiny clay statue of the local deity Shakudiya Maharaj, and loose change finds a place to hide…maybe then, even if only in someone’s memories, I will find a way to live here in the mountains after all.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 17 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://darbadar.com/stories/2015/08/sewa/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://darbadar.com/stories/2015/08/sewa/</guid>
        
        <category>Travel</category>
        
        <category>Adventure</category>
        
        <category>India</category>
        
        <category>Himalayas</category>
        
        <category>Garhwal</category>
        
        <category>Trek</category>
        
        <category>RupinPass</category>
        
        <category>Uttarakhand</category>
        
        <category>People</category>
        
        
        <category>post</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Pen: in search of idol makers</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Harsha and I looked outside the window, careful not to brush our shoulders against the piece of chewed gum stuck to the edge of the window frame. The bus was wedged in a narrow alley between makeshift shops with tin roofs, raucous hawkers selling their wares on hand carts, people scuttling along, careful not to step into the open drains that ran along the road, all populating a claustrophobic space. It could have been any town, its appearance nondescript, but deceivingly so, as we would discover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bus-stop was a few kilometers away but we got down early. As the &lt;em&gt;lal dabba&lt;/em&gt;(translation: red box), a term used to describe MSRTC(Maharashtra State Road Transport Corporation) buses, trudged along in a drunken stupor, we made our way across the road to a small workshop hiding behind blue plastic covers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workshop, only slightly bigger than a closet, housed a bunch of rusted steel racks, their tops touching the roof and filled with brooms, paints and Ganesh idols, all jostling for space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were in Pen, a town in Raigad district of Maharashtra, India, famous for its Ganesh idols that are sold in Pune, Mumbai, Nagpur, Pandharpur, and even exported to USA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like most of our travel plans, this one too hit us quite unexpectedly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started with talking about Ganesh Chaturthi, then about Lokmanya Tilak’s role in re-inventing this domestic festival into a public event and somehow ended with wondering about the birthplace of Ganesh idols.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;Can we sit here and watch while you work?&quot;&gt;“Hum yahan baith ke dekh sakte hain?”&lt;/em&gt; Harsha asked one of the artisans in the workshop, busy at work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;Yes, sure!&quot;&gt;“Haan, bilkul!”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We watched in awe as he dipped his brush in black paint and drew the curve of the idol’s eyelid in a single stroke. I don’t think Harsha would have achieved that level of perfection even with a compass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;How many years have you been doing this for?&quot;&gt;“Aap ye kitne saalon se kar rahe hain?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;For 25 years&quot;&gt;“Pachchis saal se,”&lt;/em&gt;he said and spun the wooden disc to move on to the next idol. He was working on four idols simultaneously, no two idols being the same. Facing four different directions, they were all mounted on a wooden disc with an axle, the mechanism beneath it hidden inside the hole in the ground covered by two rotting planks of wood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/259/20242981198_887196bc14_c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Man painting the tilak and eyes of idol&quot; data-caption=&quot;One would think that he works with just two colours, black and white. No. A touch of yellow, a hint of blue...so much effort, such details, and to think that most of these would go down a filthy water body somewhere...&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A woman in her late twenties sat some distance away painting the &lt;em&gt;dhotis&lt;/em&gt; on the idols, occasionally looking up at us and smiling awkwardly. A 	seventeen year old gave finishing touches to the idols, coating them with varnish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We realized then, and confirmed that every artisan in that workshop and others that were to follow, work on specific parts of the idol. One artisan paints the eyes, another does the basic colouring, a third does the shading work, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;How did you learn to do this?&quot;&gt;“Aap ne ye kaam seekha kaise?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;I have been good at drawing right from my childhood days, used to win every competition in school. I got a hang of it once I started working.&quot;&gt;“Bachpan se drawing me achcha tha, sab competition jeet ta tha school me. Karte karte seekh gaya.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After asking them a few more questions, we took leave and made our way through narrow lanes in search of another workshop. After being misdirected about half a dozen times, and caught unaware by a sudden spurt of heavy rain that Harsha believed to be a cloudburst, we finally stumbled across another workshop after half an hour, this one being much larger than the last one. The moment we stepped inside, we were greeted by a rather curious sight: tiny clay hands, fresh out of moulds, left to dry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/556/19799579713_dfb34c7199_c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ganesh Hands in making&quot; data-caption=&quot;If not for the idols placed behind, this could just as well be spotted on the sets of a horror movie.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;Are you from IT?&quot;&gt;“Tumhi IT wale aahat ka?”&lt;/em&gt; asked one of the artisans busy painting Lord Ganesha’s nails a bright red.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;How do you know that we work in IT?&quot;&gt;“Tumhala kasa kalala ke aamhi ITat kaam karto,”&lt;/em&gt; asked Harsha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;Ritesh! Come here!&quot;&gt;“Ae Ritesh! Ikde ye!”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A man, who until now had been tuning the radio while he took a break from fixing a broken idol, got up and came running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;Tell madam to come immediately, the IT people have come.&quot;&gt;“Madam la bolav, laukar saang, IT wale aale aahet,”&lt;/em&gt; he whispered into his ears with a great sense of urgency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;Why don&#39;t you sit here madam?&quot;&gt;“Ithe basa na madam,”&lt;/em&gt; he said getting up and flashing a toothless grin. &lt;em title=&quot;Will you like to have some tea?&quot;&gt;“Tumhi chaha ghenar?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;Please don&#39;t call us madam. And there is no need to get tea either. We just want to see how you work...&quot;&gt;“Aap madam mat bulaiye. Aur chai ki bhi zaroorat nahi. Hum bas thoda dekhna chahte hai, ki aap kaam kaise karte hain…”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;Madam, our madam (boss) will come in some time...she will tell you everything, how many idols we make, how much money we make, how much taxes we pay, everything...our workshop is forty years old, we don&#39;t do anything illegal.&quot;&gt;“Madam, hamari badi madam abhi ayengi…wo apko sab bata deyengi, hum kitna moorti banate, kitna paisa banate, kitna tax dete, sab…hamara kaarkhana chaalis saal purana hai, kabhi kuch lochcha nahi kiya humne.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harsha and I looked at each other in surprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Hello,” said a frail lady who had just stepped outside the house, the open space beside which was being used as a workshop, a yellow plastic sheet for a roof.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Hi!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We just want to take a look…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If you will step inside, we can show you the records from last year, the number of idols we have sold, all our financial records…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We just want to see the artisans working, that’s all.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Aren’t you from the income tax department?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“No…oh! We work in the IT industry, information technology…at least she does, she is a programmer,” I said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;Oh! Uncle, they are not from income tax department. IT implies people who work in the field of computers.&quot;&gt;“Oh! Arrey kaka, te income tax department che nahiye! IT manjhe computer war kaam karnare lok.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;Mahesh, you are such a fool!&quot;&gt;“Kay veda aahes tu Mahesh!”&lt;/em&gt; said a voice, hidden from our view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;I saw their cameras and thought...remember the last time when people from income tax department came and took photos...&quot;&gt;“Arrey! Me tyaanche cameras baghitle ani mala vatla…athavta, magchya velis income tax department che lok ale hote ani photos ghetle hote…”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His explanation was drowned in laughter and the same voice teasing him: &lt;em title=&quot;Fool!&quot;&gt;“Veda!”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We peeked behind a wooden rack overwhelmed by Ganesh idols and spotted the source of the voice. A seventy year old man sat there having a hearty laugh, spatula in hand and working on a clay idol, yet to be painted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/333/20430991035_bb2cb006cc_c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Old man working on clay model&quot; data-caption=&quot;He continued to laugh for a good five minutes. Something tells us that he is still teasing Mahesh.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em title=&quot;Trishna, I am pretty sure we would have reached faster walking backwards.&quot;&gt;“Yaar Trishna, ulte chalke bhi isse jaldi pahunchte hum log,”&lt;/em&gt; said Harsha, sitting opposite me in the six-seater.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stood just in time to save my behind from further suffering as the vehicle landed into a ditch, one of several that the entire stretch of the road was infected with. We were on our way to Hamrapur village, 7 kms away from Pen. After visiting several workshops in Pen and speaking to various artisans, we were directed towards Hamrapur village when we told them that we were eager to see the process of the idols being extracted from moulds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Seriously! On a completely different note, I think my bum might have gone into a vegetative state.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workshops in Hamrapur were quite different from the ones we saw in Pen. Twenty feet idols were a common sight. As were hundreds of idols arranged in rows with military precision. These workshops looked like factories. And unlike the workshops in Pen where the artisans appeared to be underpaid but happy, these guys strictly meant business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/277/20411915602_c83cfb568b_c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ganesh Idols&quot; data-caption=&quot;For eight months, only white idols like these are seen everywhere, they are painted four months before the festival.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Hamrapur, in addition to seeing moulds that are used to create these idols, we understood the process of their creation: a thin layer of POP(Plaster of Paris) is poured into a mould which is then covered with coir brought from Tamil Nadu. Once the POP dries, the idol is then extracted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/560/19808365154_f30922df1a_c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ganesh Idol with back open&quot; data-caption=&quot;We were quite surprised to see square shaped openings like these behind large idols, reminded us of dolls that kids play with.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having seen all that we needed to, we endured another painful six-seater ride back to Pen. We would board a bus after that and make our way back to Pune through the scenic Lonavala ghat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pen is not a pretty place. But the artisans who reside there, lend a certain character to it that is unforgettable. Underpaid, overworked and still perfectly happy doing what they have been for several decades now, these artisans are just as extraordinary as their creations. And for that reason alone, we will remember Pen. Not for the terribly suffocating humidity that invaded us that day. Not for the unruly four and a half hours bus ride from Pune to Pen. Not even for the young artisans in a workshop in Hamrapur village we nearly had to run away from, for our safety. The warmth and humility of its gifted people who let us take a glimpse into their world, that’s all we will remember Pen for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Harsha and I sift through the images we captured on our trip, there is one that catches my eye: an artisan polishing a clay hand before he attaches it to the idol sitting in front of him. I can’t help but smile at the irony: the man who supposedly God created, was now creating Him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/278/20411915792_928140b68f_c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The creator and his creation&quot; data-caption=&quot;The creator and the creation, who is who?&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://darbadar.com/stories/2015/08/pen/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://darbadar.com/stories/2015/08/pen/</guid>
        
        <category>Travel</category>
        
        <category>Maharashtra</category>
        
        <category>India</category>
        
        <category>Culture</category>
        
        <category>Festivals</category>
        
        <category>Ganeshotsav</category>
        
        <category>Konkan</category>
        
        <category>Idols</category>
        
        <category>RuralIndia</category>
        
        
        <category>post</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
